Boker tov, today's דף daf is נ"ב. nun bet. We pick up
at the bottom of נ"א עמוד ב'. nun alef amud bet. We
have just started a משנה Mishna and we sort of shifted from
discussions of what types of things are connected to an עבודה זרה,
avoda zara, איסור בהנאה, issur bahana'ah, תקרובת, tikroves, all of those issues,
to the statement in the משנה Mishna about when an actual idol
becomes forbidden in benefit. So our סתם משנה stam Mishna said that
it becomes of an idol of a non-Jew becomes forbidden as soon
as it's made, but of a Jew only once it's worshipped. So
we're going to now spend the day looking at a debate between
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva exactly on that
point where they adopt sort of mirror image positions of one another.
So two dots at the two dots נ"א עמוד ב' nun alef
amud bet about ten lines from the bottom. עבודת כוכבים של עובד
כוכבים אסורה מיד. Avodas kochavim shel oveid kochavim asura miyad. The idol
of a non-Jew is forbidden immediately. מתניתין מני רבי עקיבא היא Masnisin
mani? Rabbi Akiva hee. Who's our משנה? Mishna? It's
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. דתניא: D'tanya: אבד תאבדון את כל המקומות אשר
עבדו שם הגוים, Abeid t'abdun es kol hamakomos asher avdu sham hagoyim,
את אלהיהם es eloheihem is the end of the verse. So destroy
all the places that they worshipped.
והכלים שנשתמשו בהן לעבודה זרה הכתוב מדבר. V'hakeilim shenishtamshu bahen l'avoda zara,
hakasuv midabeir. This is actually not talking about the places because as
we'll see, as we know, you're not going to go whatever raise
the mountain or something like that, destroy the actual physical location, landscape,
and you don't have to, אלהיהם על ההרים. eloheihem al heharim. So
it's not talking about the actual places, it's talking about vessels that
were used to do the service like תשמישי עבודה זרה. tashmishei avoda
zara. That's the way נשתמשו. nishtamshu. Okay, that you have to destroy.
יכול עשאום ולא גמרום גמרום ולא הביאום הביאום ולא נשתמשו בהן יכול
יהיו אסורין. Yachol asahum v'lo gamrum, gamrum v'lo hevi'um, hevi'um v'lo nishtamshu
bahen, yachol yiheyu asurin. Maybe if you made them but you didn't
finish them, or you finished them but you didn't exactly bring them
into the temple, the idolatrous temple, or you brought them in but
you didn't actually use them, meaning maybe they'd be forbidden at an
earlier stage? תלמוד לומר אשר עבדו שם הגוים, Talmud lomar asher avdu
sham hagoyim, that they worshipped there. So again, although the verse is
talking about the place, we're talking about the object used in the
worship, שאין
אסורין עד שיעבדו. she'ein asurin ad sheye'aveidu. They're not forbidden until they're
used in worship. Now that's in terms of תשמישי עבודה זרה. tashmishei
avoda zara. But now we're going to make, and that actually everybody
agrees, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, that they
agree to that read of the beginning of the verse, that it's
תשמישי עבודה זרה, tashmishei avoda zara, and that it's forbidden only once
it's actually used. But now רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is going to
jump from that to the idol itself. Okay? מכאן אמרו
עבודת כוכבים של עובד כוכבים אינה אסורה עד שתעבד. Mikan amru: avodas
kochavim shel oveid kochavim einah asura ad shete'aveid. From this הלכה halacha
about the תשמישי עבודה זרה, tashmishei avoda zara, they went and they
said that even the idol is not forbidden until it's actually worshipped.
ושל ישראל אסורה מיד, V'shel yisrael asura miyad, but a Jew is
forbidden right away. דברי רבי ישמעאל. Divrei Rabbi Yishmael. That's the words
of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. So excuse me, I said, I said
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, the משנה Mishna is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
because the משנה Mishna takes the opposite position. But the first position
here this ברייתא braisa is: תשמישי עבודה זרה tashmishei avoda zara is
forbidden when it is used. Everybody agrees to that, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael and רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. But רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael is
now inferring from that that the idol itself is only forbidden once
it's worshipped. Our משנה Mishna said the idol was forbidden immediately. But
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael is saying, no, it's like the תשמישים. tashmishim.
The idol of a non-Jew is forbidden only once it's worshipped. And
then it's not clear where he learns that the ישראל Yisrael is
the inverse. But both רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael and רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva, although they're mirror images, they both agree that the ישראל Yisrael
is the inverse of the non-Jew. So once we've established that a
non-Jew is only once it's worshipped, a Jew is as soon as
it's made. Yes Michael?
No I was going to say that this obviously, we know that
this contrasts with what we were learning before, like the אשרה asheira
we said it has, if it's פסיסת ידי אדם p'sisas yedei adam
and
it's ואילנו נטעו מכך.
v'inlo nit'u mikach. You mean there are cases where the actual landscape
can be forbidden. But that was debated,
and so we don't have an interest in reading it that way.
רבי עקיבא אומר חילוף הדברים. Rabbi Akiva omer: chiluf hadvarim. Now רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says it's the exact inverse. עבודת כוכבים של עובד
כוכבים אסורה מיד, Avodas kochavim shel oveid kochavim asura miyad, that which
this is our משנה. Mishna. The idol of a non-Jew is forbidden
immediately. ושל ישראל עד שתעבד, V'shel yisrael ad shete'aveid, and a Jew
only once it's worshipped. And he doesn't give a verse. So now
we have to unpack all of this. אמר מר בכלים שנשתמשו בהן
לעבודה זרה הכתוב מדבר. Amar mar: b'keilim shenishtamshu bahen l'avoda zara, hakasuv
midabeir. The one source that we have in this ברייתא braisa is
this אשר עבדו שם הגוים asher avdu sham hagoyim that we're saying
that it's talking actually not about the place, but about objects that
were used in the worship.
המקומות כתיב. Hamakomos ksiv. מר Mar says what do you mean objects?
It says the places that they worshipped. אם אינו ענין למקומות. Im
einu inyan l'makomos. מר Mar says, no, but you can't read the
פסוק pasuk like that way according to the that פשט pshat reading
wouldn't fit the הלכה, halacha, ולא מצריעי v'lo mitzre'ei because places are
not forbidden. דכתיב אלהיהם על ההרים ולא ההרים אלהיהם. D'ksiv: eloheihem al
heharim v'lo heharim eloheihem. Their gods on the mountains, the mountains cannot
be considered their gods, the places themselves do not become forbidden. So
if it is talking about destroying it must not mean the places,
it must mean the objects of worship. So therefore, תני ענין לכלים.
Tenei inyan l'keilim. Talk about the objects of worship. Okay, fine. That's
the idea that תשמישי עבודה זרה tashmishei avoda zara is only once
they're used and everybody agrees to that, both רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
and רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. But רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael jumps from
that to say the same is true about the idol itself. מכאן
אמרו עבודת כוכבים של עובד כוכבים אינה אסורה עד שתעבד. Mikan amru:
avodas kochavim shel oveid kochavim einah asura ad shete'aveid. ושל ישראל מיד.
V'shel yisrael miyad. So the גמרא Gemara says how did you get
from תשמישי עבודה זרה tashmishei avoda zara to the idol itself? והא
בכלים אוקימנא לה. V'ha b'keilim okimna lah. You just got through saying
that that was about the actual objects that were used in the
worship. How did you get from there that the idol itself is
only... forbidden once it's worshipped. אמר קרא, Amar kra, the end of
the verse is אשר אתם יורשים אותם את אלוהיהם, asher atem yorshim
osam es eloheihem, אבד תאבדון את כל המקומות אשר עבדו שם הגוים,
abed te'avedun es kol hamakomos asher avdu sham hagoyim, אשר אתם יורשים
אותם את אלוהיהם. asher atem yorshim osam es eloheihem. Okay, destroy all
the places that the non-Jews worshipped, which means the objects of worship,
that you are, right,
you are
dispossessing them, thank you, dispossessing them and their gods. So the idea
to destroy the objects of worship is now connected with and their
gods. So in the same way the objects of worship is only
once they're used, their gods are also only forbidden once they're used.
אשר אתם יורשים אותם את אלוהיהם. asher atem yorshim osam es eloheihem.
מקיש אלוהיהם לכלים, makish eloheihem lechelim, it connects their gods to the
vessels. מה כלים עד שיעבדו אף אלוהיהם נמי עד שיעבדו. ma keilim
ad sheye'avedu af eloheihem nami ad sheye'avedu. Okay, so we're just going
to put it all in this together. That's how you get the
objects of worship only once they're used and the idols once they're
used. ורבי עקיבא, veRabbi Akiva, now רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva concedes that
the objects of worship, the תשמישים, tashmishim, are only once they're used.
But he says you can't jump from there to the idols. Why
not? דלא מקיש, delo makish, he doesn't connect the objects of worship
to the idols or the תשמישים, tashmishim, I'll just call them תשמישים
tashmishim to the idols. אמר לך את הפסיק העניין. amar lach es
hifsik hainyan. It says אשר אתם יורשים
אותם, asher atem yorshim osam, את אלוהיהם. es eloheihem. Okay, so the
את אלוהיהם es eloheihem is already a new topic. So even though
yes, it mentions their gods at the end of the verse, but
that's not connected to the destroying the תשמישי עבודה זרה. tashmishei avoda
zara. תשמישי עבודה זרה tashmishei avoda zara is when they're used, their
gods, that's a different story. Okay,
ורבי ישמעאל אשכחן עבודת כוכבים של עובד כוכבים דאינה אסורה עד שתעבד.
veRabbi Yishmael ashchan avodas kochavim shel oved kochavim de'eina asura ad shete'aved.
Fine. We got the verse according to רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. It's
talking about their תשמישים tashmishim and the idols only once they're worshipped,
that we get. דישראל דאסורה מיד מנלן? deYisroel de'asura miyad minalan? Where
does he get the flip by the ישראל? Yisroel? 'Cause you know,
where does he get the idea that it's what's the exact opposite
of what's true by the non-Jews is true by the ישראל? Yisroel?
Where does he get that from? So the first answer is, סברא
הוא. savara hu. It's just a logical. מדאובד כוכבים עד שתעבד ישראל
אסורה מיד. mide'oved kochavim ad shete'aved Yisroel asura miyad.
You know logically, Jews should be different than non-Jews. So if the
non-Jews is only once it's worshipped, the Jews is immediately. Which the
גמרא Gemara is going to ask in a minute like what type
of סברא savara is that? So the גמרא Gemara says אימא דישראל
כלל כלל לא. eima deYisroel klal klal lo. Wait wait wait. First
of all, אימא דישראל כלל כלל לא. eima deYisroel klal klal lo.
Maybe, let's make a radical suggestion. Maybe a Jew who worships an
idol the idol is never forbidden? Only non-Jewish idols are forbidden. We
of course know the opposite, that if a Jew worships an idol
there's no way it could become permissible afterward. But the גמרא Gemara
is going to say how do you know that? אימא דישראל כלל
כלל לא. eima deYisroel klal klal lo. No, השתא גניזה בעיא איצורי
לא מצרא? hashta gniza ba'ya itzurei lo mitzra? You have to go
ahead and bury it. We're going to find out in a moment
from a פסוק pasuk that it says, that it says ושם בסתר.
vesam basaser. Place it in hiding. That it tells you that if
an object a Jewish a Jew worships an idol and it's whatever,
that it cannot be used at all. It has to be placed
away. I'll get back to that in a minute, but no, clearly
it's forbidden. We're going to we know that a Jew's idol is
also forbidden. Okay, so still how do you know that it's not
the same as a non-Jew?
ואימא כעובד כוכבים? ve'eima ke'oved kochavim? Okay, שכוייח. shkoiach. But I still
don't get your logic that the Jew should obviously be different than
the non-Jew. Maybe it's just like the non-Jew, maybe they're both only
once they're worshipped. אמר קרא ואת חטאתכם אשר עשיתם את העגל. amar
kra ve'es chataschem asher asisem es ha'egel. Your sin that you made
the עגל. egel. So משעת עשייה קם ליה בחטא. mishas asiya kam
lei becheit. As soon as you made it, that was the sin.
Now of course just 'cause it's a sin doesn't mean that the
object is forbidden. So the גמרא Gemara says exactly that. אימא הני
מילי למיקם גברא בחטא. eima hanei mili lemikam gavra becheit. That's when
you did your sin by making the object. איצורי לא מיצרא. itzurei
lo mitzra. But who says that it's forbidden at that time? Like
we had all those discussions the other day about תקרובת. tikroves. There's
certain things that could make you חייב מיתה chayav misa that don't
affect the status of the object. So
fine. Maybe this is the transgression of making the idols, making gods,
and you're making them for the purpose of worship, but it doesn't
yet mean that it has that status. Okay, so אמר
קרא amar kra another verse says ארור האיש אשר יעשה פסל ומסכה
תועבת ה' ושם בסתר. arur ha'ish asher ya'ase pesel umasecha to'avas Hashem
vesam basaser. Okay, we're going to get to that the ושם בסתר
vesam basaser is in a minute of how we're going to know
that you can't get benefit. Cursed is the man that makes
an a god an idol or a graven image. Okay, so משעת
עשייה קאי בארור. mishas asiya kai be'arur. As soon as he makes
it he's being cursed. אשר
יעשה. asher ya'ase. So the גמרא Gemara says same question though. אימא
הני מילי למיקם גברא בארור. eima hanei mili lemikam gavra be'arur. That's
when he's cursed. Okay, איצורי לא מיצרא. itzurei lo mitzra. But it's
not yet forbidden as an object. So גמרא Gemara says no, תועבת
ה' כתיב. to'avas Hashem ksiv. The thing is an abomination of God,
not the action, but you know, אשר יעשה פסל ומסכה תועבת ה'.
asher ya'ase pesel umasecha to'avas Hashem. That describes the object. So for
the object to be labeled תועבת ה', to'avas Hashem, it means the
object is forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah. That's when the object has its
status. Okay, so that seems to be a pretty good proof that
for ישראל Yisroel it's only as soon as it's made. So ורבי
עקיבא... veRabbi Akiva... How would Rabbi Akiva counter this? We haven't yet
shown where Rabbi Akiva gets his position. We'll get to that in
a minute. But since we know Rabbi Akiva says a Jew's idol
is only when it's worshipped, what does he do with the fact
that the verse calls it תועבת ה׳ toavat Hashem from the moment
it's made? So Rabbi Akiva, דבר המביא לידי תועבה, davar hameivi lidei
toevah, okay, it's תועבת ה׳ toavat Hashem not because הלכתית halachically it's
אסור בהנאה, asur behana'ah, it's תועבת ה׳ toavat Hashem because it's going
to lead to idol worship. Okay, so it's sort of like it's
a, you know, it's religiously descriptive. It's not הלכתית halachically descriptive.
נפקא מינה nafka mina for having, I don't know, a cross back
there, right?
Yeah, that's an interesting question. If you're making it not for you
to worship it and yeah, there's exactly all those issues. Okay, so
anyway, so now we've got the, okay, so we've got what do
we have? We've got
Rabbi Ishmael learns it out from תשמישי עבודה זרה tashmishei avodah zarah
is only once they're used. That tells you about the idols themselves.
He makes that link. Rabbi Akiva doesn't make that link. And ישראל
Yisrael we know because of this verse that talks about when you
make it it's תועבת ה׳. toavat Hashem. And that's how the ישראל
Yisrael is the inverse. Now, where is Rabbi Akiva get to be
the exact mirror image of that? Okay, ורבי עקיבא, ve-Rabbi Akiva, that's
Rabbi Ishmael, that's not our Mishnah. Rabbi Akiva, עבודת כוכבים של עובד
כוכבים אסורה מיד. avodat kochavim shel oveid kochavim asurah mi-yad. Rabbi Akiva
says that it's forbidden immediately, which is our Mishnah, a non-Jew. מנא
ליה, minaleih, where does he know that from? אמר עולא אמר קרא,
amar Ulla amar kra, פסילי אלוהיהם תשרפון באש. psilei eloheihem tisrefun ba-esh.
Their,
the images of their gods, the idols of their gods you should
burn in fire. So the word פסל, pesel, לפסול lifsol means to
like hew, like פסל לך שני לוחות אבנים כראשונים. psol lecha shenei
luchot avanim ka-rishonim. Right, it's very funny, that whole big פסוק pasuk
right that we read, you know, on the תענית ta'anit or whatever,
פסל לך, psol lecha, it has that word פסל pesel in it,
right? The stones. That's always the issue. Is something carved, does that
become an עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, does that become a substitute for
God? Okay, so פסילי אלוהיהם תשרפון באש, psilei eloheihem tisrefun ba-esh, משפסלו,
mi-she-psalo, from the moment you carved it, נעשה אלוהיה. na'asah eloheiha. פסילי
אלוהיהם. psilei eloheihem. Its status as a god and also the obligation
to destroy, you could say, the תשרפון באש tisrefun ba-esh is from
the moment it's carved. That's Rabbi Akiva. That's for non-Jews. Okay, ואידך,
ve-idach, so
what would Rabbi Ishmael say to that? הוא מיבעי ליה לכדתניא רב
יוסף. hu mibaei leih le-chid-tanya Rav Yosef. No, it's telling you something
else, like Rav Yosef. דתניא רב יוסף, de-tanya Rav Yosef, מניין לעובד
כוכבים שפוסל אלוהו. minayin le-oveid kochavim she-posel eloho. אלוהו, eloho, I guess
yeah. Anyway,
how do you know a non-Jew can do the ביטול? bittul? Okay,
we're going to get to ביטול bittul in a coming up Mishnah.
Should get him to לא כוכבים? lo kochavim? No, what? Exactly. How
do you know that a non-Jew can invalidate his own god? שנאמר,
shene'emar,
פסילי אלוהיהם תשרפון באש. psilei eloheihem tisrefun ba-esh. So the word פסל
pesel we're learning from the word לפסול lifsol to invalidate. That's the
principle about ביטול עבודה זרה. bittul avodah zarah. And we don't have
that by a Jew, which is why a Jew can't be מבטל
עבודה זרה. mevattel avodah zarah. Okay. Well, I mean, it's תשרפון באש,
tisrefun ba-esh, once he's מפסל mefassel
you don't have to.
Right, I know. ואידך, ve-idach, and what would Rabbi Akiva say back?
נפקא ליה מדשמואל. nafka leih mid-Shmuel. He learns out the idea that
a non-Jew does ביטול עבודה זרה bittul avodah zarah from Shmuel. דשמואל
רמי, de-Shmuel rami, Shmuel showed a contradiction. כתיב, ktiv, לא תחמוד כסף
וזהב עליהם. lo tachmod kesef ve-zahav aleihem. It says, don't desire, covet
the gold and silver on the idols. וכתיב, u-ktiv, and the verse
says, ולקחת לך. ve-lakachta lach. Take it for yourself. לא תחמוד, lo
tachmod, no, don't! I know, it's like, it's like, it's like what
is it? It's like לא תרצח, lo tirtsach, וענו בדוקי. ve-annu badokei.
Right, right, right.
I know,
it's always the question where you put the emphasis, right? What? לא
תרצח? lo tirtsach? You know what I mean? ועבדתם אלוהים אחרים. ve-avadtem
elohim acherim. Okay,
so anyway, right? So okay, yes, it's a very funny read of
the verse, but he is reading, don't desire, comma, take it. So
הא כיצד, ha keitzad, how do you read that? פסלו לאלוהו, psalo
le-eloho, if it's, if you invalidated it, לא תחמוד. lo tachmod. Okay,
I'm sorry. פסלו, psalo, excuse me, if he carved it as a
god, then it's a play on the word פסל. pesel. If you
carved it as a god, לא תחמוד, lo tachmod, don't desire it.
פסלו מאלוהו, psalo me-eloho, if he invalidated it from being a god,
ולקחת לך, ve-lakachta lach, and then you can take it. All right,
so whatever, he learns it somewhere else. But the word פסילי אלוהיהם,
psilei eloheihem, Rabbi Akiva learns to say that that's from the moment
it's carved it's a god, and the Rabbi Ishmael would say back,
no, that's the idea of invalidating it, ביטול עבודה זרה. bittul avodah
zarah. Okay, that's where Rabbi Akiva gets an idol of a non-Jew
is immediate. ורבי עקיבא, ve-Rabbi Akiva, how does this contradiction,
are you ever allowed to gain any benefit from after ביטול? bittul?
You can, after ביטול.
bittul. Yes, you can't use it for like a בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash purpose, but yes, that's the whole idea of ביטול. bittul. Right?
Remember we had before the stones from the מרקוליס Merkulis were paving
the road and all that stuff.
ורבי עקיבא ve-Rabbi Akiva
now,
Rabbi
Akiva would say, אז כאן עבודת כוכבים של עובד כוכבים אסורה מיד.
az kan avodat kochavim shel oveid kochavim asurah mi-yad. Now, I mean,
now we say according to Rabbi Akiva, one minute, okay, good. We
got that a non-Jew's idol's forbidden immediately because it says פסילי אלוהיהם
psilei eloheihem תשרפון באש. tisrefun ba-esh. ישראל עד שתעבד מנלן? Yisrael ad
she-tei'aveid minalan?
Where do you know a Jew's until it's worshipped? So אמר רב
יהודה אמר קרא, amar Rav Yehudah amar kra, the verse says, ושם
בסתר, ve-sam ba-sater, ושם בסתר ve-sam ba-sater
I think. ארור האיש אשר יעשה פסל ומסכה תועבת ה׳ ושם בסתר.
arur ha-ish asher ya'aseh pesel u-maseichah toavat Hashem ve-sam ba-sater. Cursed is
the man that makes an idol and places it in hiding to
like worship it in private. So what we're going to learn is,
עד שיעשה לה דברים שבסתר, ad she-ya'aseh lah devarim she-ba-sater,
until he does that, those secret things that he's planning on doing
with it, which is worshipping it. So only once it's ושם בסתר,
ve-sam ba-sater, only once he actually... only worships it, then is it
considered to be an idol. ואידך, veidach, what would what would Rabbi
Yishmael say back? ההוא מיבעי ליה לדרבי יצחק, hehu mibei lei ledarabbi
Yitzchak, דאמר רבי יצחק, damar rabbi Yitzchak, מניין לעבודת כוכבים של ישראל
שטעונה גניזה. minayin lavodat kochavim shel Yisrael sheteunah genizah. This is what
we alluded to before. How do you know that you're not allowed
to get benefit from an idol of a not of a Jew?
We know by a non-Jew it says destroy it, etc. How do
we know you're not allowed to get benefit from an from a
Jew? I'm going to get to the word גניזה genizah in a
minute. I'm going to get to the word גניזה genizah in a
minute. I will get to that in a minute. שנאמר, shenemar, because
the verse says ושם בסתר, vesam basater,
place it in hiding, which means just bury it, don't get any
benefit.
ואידך, veidach, and also that's where he's putting it. Saying this is
what you should do.
This is what you should do with it. Sort of like the
ולקחת לך, velakachta lach, okay, where as opposed to being descriptive or
whatever and part of the previous thing, we're reading it as prescriptive
and separate. Okay, right, it's parallel, interesting. ואידך, veidach, now Rabbi Akiva
who reads the verse more כפשוטו, kipshto, that he's placing it in
hiding in order to worship it and it's only forbidden when it's
worshiped, where does he learn the idea that it becomes forbidden? נפקא
ליה מדרב חסדא, nafka lei miderav Chisda, from Rav Chisda. אמר רב,
amar Rav, דאמר רב חסדא אמר רב, damar Rav Chisda amar Rav,
מניין לעבודת כוכבים של ישראל שטעונה גניזה. minayin lavodat kochavim shel Yisrael
sheteunah genizah. How do you know that you have to bury it,
you can't get benefit? שנאמר, shenemar, the verse says לא תטע לך
אשרה כל עץ אצל מזבח. lo tita lecha asherah kol etz etzel
mizbeiach. Don't plant an אשרה asherah by the altar of God. מה
מזבח טעון גניזה, mah mizbeiach taun genizah, the same way an altar
if the stones became somehow unusable, okay, you can't just throw them
out, you have to bury them.
How do you know how do you know that?
But you have to ask. Yeah, it's true. Anyway, it's הקדש. hekdesh.
We're assuming we know that from the fact that it's הקדש. hekdesh.
Okay, אף אשרה טעונה גניזה. af asherah teunah genizah.
The same is true by an אשרה. asherah. ואידך, veidach, what would
the other one learn from that verse? Since he doesn't need to
learn from the verse the idea of גניזה. genizah. So ואידך, veidach,
הוא מיבעי ליה לריש לקיש, hu mibei lei lerish lakish, like Reish
Lakish. דאמר ריש לקיש, damar rish lakish, כל המעמיד דיין שאינו הגון.
kol hamaamid dayan sheino hagun. I'll tell you a religious principle. כל
המעמיד דיין שאינו הגון כאילו נוטע אשרה בישראל. kol hamaamid dayan sheino
hagun keilu noteia asherah beYisrael. If you if you if you establish
an unfit judge, it's like you planted an אשרה. asherah. Meaning since
the whole idea of judges is to like establish God's justice and
God's law in the land, so the intertwining of idolatry and, you
know, perverted justice, because it's perverting God's rule and God's presence, you
know, God's presence in this society is based on our establishing God's
law, okay? שנאמר, shenemar, is the verse says שופטים ושוטרים תיתן לך
בכל שעריך, shoftim veshotrim titein lecha bechol shearecha, וסמיך ליה לא תטע
לך אשרה כל עץ. vesamich lei lo tita lecha asherah kol etz.
So juxtaposed to making judges is not planting an אשרה. asherah. Fine.
ואמר רב אשי, vaamar Rav Ashi, במקום תלמידי חכמים. bemakom talmidei chachamim.
Now if you make these perverted justices, these un-these, you know, these
corrupt judges where there are actually Torah sages who could be better
judges and where it's more a clear affront to the real truth
of the Torah, כאילו נטע אצל מזבח. keilu nata etzel mizbeiach. It's
not like just that you planted and did idolatry, it's like you
did idolatry right by the altar. שנאמר עץ אצל מזבח. shenemar etz
etzel mizbeiach. Okay, so that's the end. So now we're done with
that section, just learning it out from the various verses and we
have our basic principles about these mirror images. So I wanted to
take a minute to discuss two things. One is like which position
makes more sense, Rabbi Akiva or Rabbi Ishmael. I'm just curious what
you think and what's the logic behind the positions. And the other
is this idea of גניזה genizah that was mentioned by that of
a ישראל, Yisrael, which is a little disturbing that word or whatever
the concept connecting it to מזבח mizbeiach and so on. So let's
first talk about let me ask a question before I answer it.
Okay, let me pause. So let's first talk about which one makes
more sense. Does it make more sense to think that a, you
know, that a non-Jew should be immediately and a Jew only once
it's worshiped or the reverse? So Michael has an opinion.
Well, I think the Jew should be אסור assur right away. Yeah,
because it's such a bigger affront to God for like a Jew
making, a non-Jew is okay, we understand that's what they do, but
Jews, oh my god, that's terrible. So, you know, so right away
or you know, but I also see the other side, you know,
to say like, well listen, you know, a Jew like he doesn't
really want to worship it, you know, we don't want to really
think that they that they're into this. So, you know, we'll just
push it off later, maybe he'll do תשובה teshuvah or something, you
know, whereas a non-Jew, you know, we know they're just going to
worship it so it'll be אסור assur right away.
Yeah, so I think you can make both arguments. Initially I thought
the second one, sort of like the גמרא Gemara that says about
you can't you're allowed to do business with a Jew that's on
his way to an idolatrous festival because you're going to assume he'll
do תשובה teshuvah before he gets there. You know, so like we
don't want to assume even if a Jew is making an idol,
we sort of don't want to assume that it's, oh, it's already
as if it's worshiped, it already has its status. Like we want
to hope for the best outcome there. Whereas for a non-Jew, like
we're just assuming that's what the business that they're in, you know,
of course they're going to use it and whatever and it's already
clearly going to be used that way. You know, but I like
your you know, the flip argument might exactly be that point about
the degree of affront and so on. So it's interesting to think
like, you know, it's like if you have these mirror images, Jew
is the opposite of non-Jew and Rabbi Ishmael is the opposite of
Rabbi Akiva, it's interesting to think about like what else could inform
that those ways of thinking about it. The other thing I want
to mention, I don't know if you have any other ideas, but
I just want to put out there it's interesting to just stop
for a moment and think what this is all about.
The other issue is this issue of גניזה. genizah. So to say
that you bury the idol of a Jew is disturbing. It's first
of all it's disturbing rather than destroy it. It's disturbing first of
all because the things you bury tend to be holy things rather
than destroying them, right, you know, הקדש hekdesh or whatever we learned
it out from the מזבח. mizbeiach. Now there are some things that
are אסור בהנאה assur behanaah that you don't have to destroy and
you have to bury. You're allowed to destroy them. You're allowed to
like בשר בחלב, basar becholov, you're allowed to destroy it, but you
don't have a מצוה mitzvah to destroy it, you just have to
get it out of the way of people that nobody will benefit.
Okay, so that's the question of what does this mean by גניזה.
genizah. Does גניזה genizah mean that anything to get it out of
the way, even but not specifically גניזה? genizah? Sure, burn it, that
would be the best, destroy it, but you don't have to go
that far. Just keep it out of the way. Or does it
mean literally גניזה? genizah? So to say literally גניזה genizah is obviously
very disturbing. It's also because of the associations. It's also disturbing practically,
right? Like it would seem to me that I would rather say
that by a non-Jew's idol, don't destroy it, just keep it out
of the way, but by a Jew's idol, destroy it, like you
don't want any vestige of the idea that we as Jews worshipped
idols. Like Michael said, non-Jews, that's what they do. So you understand,
you're in the Land of Israel, you maybe want to clean out
the land, but you certainly would want to clean it out of
Jewish idols as well, right? So why it should not be as
demanding is hard to understand. If you look at תוספות, Tosfos, right,
תוספות Tosfos says מה מזבח טעון גניזה. mah mizbe'ach te'un genizah.
תוספות Tosfos says ככלי שרת אמרינן דגנוזה אף אשרה טעונה גניזה, kekli
shareis amrinan degnuza af asherah te'una genizah, פירוש ביעור
בלא הנאה. perush bi'ur belo hana'ah. It does not mean bury. It
means destroy it, don't get any pleasure.
כמו עגל ששחקו וזרוהו.
kemo egel sheshachaku vezaru'a. ומה עגל אעגלה דלמעלה אפי' רבי יוסי בן
חנינא ורבי יוחנן ורבי יוסי שכן בשוק פודא, u'me-egel eglah lame'alah afilu
Rabbi Yose bin Chanina ve-Rabbi Yochanan ve-Rabbi Yose she-kon bashuk poda, etc.
etc. etc. So
תוספות Tosfos says it means destroy it. So in the end תוספות
Tosfos says it's really just a way to get to the same
הלכה halacha by non-Jewish idols, which really means destroy it. But the
simple sense here means at least minimally means you don't have to
destroy it. It's enough to get it out of the way. And
I just find that very disturbing. The only possible explanation I could
have, but then this is disturbing on the flip, is that if
you're going with this like violence and destroying the idols or whatever,
it's not a big jump from there to you destroy their idols
and then you destroy them, right? They're all part of this evil
phenomenon and that was the הלכה halacha by the seven Canaanite nations,
destroy them and destroy their idols. So maybe that we sort of
want to be, at least by Jews we want to sort of
say, okay, just get rid of the idols, don't destroy it. Like
we don't want—of course by Jews as well, what do you do
with an עיר הנדחת? ir nidachas? You do destroy it. So I
really don't get the גניזה genizah idea as distinct from the destroying
idea by the non-Jews.
See I was thinking of the imagery of יעקב. Yaakov. I was
just thinking of burying...
Oh, that's what I thought. That יעקב Yaakov buried תחת האלה. tachas
ha'elah. Yeah,
that's a good point. Okay, it still raises the question, but you're
right, that might be informing this idea. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara continues. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. בעא רב המנונא. Ba'i
Rav Hamnuna. רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna asked the following question. ריתך כלי
לעבודת כוכבים מהו? reitech kli la'avodas kochavim mahu? Let's say somebody basically
melted down, banged, reshaped, fixed a metal vessel to use now for
עבודה זרה. avoda zara. What's its status? So the גמרא Gemara says,
wait, עבודת כוכבים דמאן? avodas kochavim de-man? First of all, does he
mean to use as a תשמיש, tashmish, to use as an עבודה
זרה? avoda zara? Let's assume he means that you did it as
an עבודה זרה. avoda zara. So who, Jews or non-Jews? אילימא עבודת
כוכבים דעובד כוכבים, ileima avodas kochavim de-oveid kochavim,
if you're saying for a non-Jew's עבודה זרה, avoda zara, בין לרבי
ישמעאל בין לרבי עקיבא משמשי עבודת כוכבים הן. bein Le-Rabbi Yishmael bein
Le-Rabbi Akiva meshamshei avodas kochavim hein. Ah,
but no, I'm sorry. So the גמרא Gemara is assuming at this
stage that you're using it as a תשמיש tashmish of עבודה זרה.
avoda zara. So a non-Jew is reshaping this fire pan, banging it,
fixing it to use as a תשמיש tashmish of עבודה זרה. avoda
zara. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, but remember רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael although they debate when the idol
becomes forbidden, they both agree that the תשמיש tashmish only becomes forbidden
once it's used. So just because you reshaped it, it's not forbidden
yet. משמשי עבודת כוכבים הם ומשמשי עבודת כוכבים אינן אסורין עד שיעבדו.
meshamshei avodas kochavim hein u'meshamshei avodas kochavim einan asurin ad she-ye'aveidu. Okay,
so the answer there is obvious if it's a תשמיש tashmish of
עבודה זרה. avoda zara. ואלא עבודת כוכבים דישראל, ve'ela avodas kochavim de-Yisrael,
fine, you want to use it as a תשמיש tashmish for a
Jewish idol. אליבא דמאן? aliba de-man? Now according to whom?
אילימא אליבא דרבי עקיבא, ileima aliba de-Rabbi Akiva, according to
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, השתא היא גופא לא מיתסרא עד שתעבד, hashta
hi gufah lo mitzra'ad she-te'aveid, if the idol itself of a Jew
is only once it's
worshipped, משמשיה מי בעיא? meshamsheha mi ba'ya? Of course actually the תשמיש
tashmish won't get that status until the object is worshipped and until
this is like used in the worship. ואלא אליבא דרבי שמעון, ve'ela
aliba de-Rabbi Shimon, fine, the question is according to רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon דאמר אסור מיד, de'amar asur mi-yad, the idol of a Jew
is forbidden
immediately. מהי? mahi? משמשי ממשמשי
גמרינן? meshamshei mi-meshamshei gamrinan? Do we learn out a תשמיש tashmish of
an idol of a Jew from a תשמיש tashmish of an idol
of a non-Jew? So the same way a תשמיש tashmish of an
idol of a non-Jew is only once it's used, the same is
true of a תשמיש tashmish of an idol of a Jew. מה
התם עד שיעבדו אף הכא עד שיעבדו, ma hasam ad she-ye'aveidu af
hacha ad she-ye'aveidu,
the same way a תשמיש tashmish of a non-Jewish idol is only
once it's used, here too only once it's used. או דילמא מינה
גמר? o dilma mineh gmar? No,
you learn the תשמיש. tashmish. from the status of the object that
it's being made for. So מה היא אסורה מיד, Ma hi asura
miyad, the same way the Jewish idol is forbidden immediately, אף תשמישיה
אסורה מיד, Af tashmisheha asura miyad,
so the תשמישים tashmishim are forbidden immediately. All right, so that's a
good question. As we know that תשמיש, tashmish, תשמישים tashmishim are forbidden
only once they're used of idols of non-Jews. What would be the
story of a תשמיש tashmish of an idol of a Jew according
to the position that the idol of a Jew is forbidden right
away? Is that תשמיש tashmish also forbidden right away or not? That's
a good question. But the גמרא Gemara says if that's your question,
מאי איריא דקמיבעיא ליה ריחטא ליה, mai irya dekamba'ei lei ritcha lei,
why are you asking this special case of reshaping a vessel? תיבעי
ליה עשה, Tiba'ei lei asah, just ask if you made a vessel,
you made a תשמיש, tashmish, when is it forbidden? So the גמרא
Gemara is now going to explain that the question was a different
one, but we're actually going to, how do you say, put this
in the parking lot. We're actually going to sort of like not
raise, not answer this question. It's an interesting question. According to the
position of רבי, Rebbi, now I'm getting, forgetting who says what, about
of רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael that the idol of a Jew is
forbidden immediately. Okay, according to that, an idol of a Jew is
forbidden immediately, when is the תשמיש tashmish of the idol of a
Jew forbidden? Okay, we don't, that we don't know the answer. תשמיש
tashmish of a non-Jew is forbidden once, only once it's used. When
is the תשמיש tashmish of an idol of a Jew forbidden if
the idol itself is forbidden immediately? We don't know the answer. But
what's this question about reshaping a vessel? So the גמרא Gemara says
רב המנונא משום, Rav Hamnuna mishum, רב המנונא, Rav Hamnuna, so תיבעי
ליה עשה. tiba'ei lei asah.
So the גמרא Gemara says רב המנונא משום טומאה ישנה קמיבעיא ליה.
Rav Hamnuna mishum tumah yeshana kamba'ei lei. He really wants to know
about, the question is not about the status of איסור הנאה. issur
hana'ah. The question is, does it become טמא? tamei? We know we've
learned already, you know, that תקרובת עבודה זרה, tikrovet avodah zarah, idols,
idols themselves, now we're sort of going to say תשמישים tashmishim which
will come up later. All these things are, have a טומאה tumah
or are impure. So you had a תשמיש tashmish of עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, it broke. So the impurity left it. Now you reshaped
it. Does the state of impurity come back? That's his question. דתנן,
Detnan, we teach. כלי מתכות פשוטיהן ומקבליהן טמאין. Klei matachot peshuteihen umekableihen
tme'in. This is a normal הלכה halacha of טומאה. tumah.
Metal vessels, whether they're flat or whether they have a receptacle component,
they are, they can become טמא. tamei.
Are they computing this just like regular טומאת כלים, tumat kelim,
is that what it's saying? Yeah, once we're saying it's טמא, tamei,
then we're giving it the normal status of anything that touched like
a dead body let's say or anything else that's טמא. tamei. Okay.
נשתברו, Nishtabru, if your metal vessel broke, טהור, tahor, טהרו, teharu, they
became pure. חזר ועשאן כלים, Chazar ve'asan kelim, you remelted,
you refashioned them, you reshaped it, יחזרו לטומאה ישנה. yachzeru letumah yeshana.
They regain their old טומאה, tumah, that's rabbinic. Okay, because of various
concerns. Okay, so that's the general rule. והכי קמיבעיא ליה, Vechi kamba'ei
lei, this was his question. כי הדרה טומאה הני מילי לטומאה דאורייתא.
Ki hadra tumah hani milei letumah d'oraita. When do we say the
טומאה tumah comes back? When it's a biblical טומאה, tumah, when the
כלי kli touched like a dead body or a you know a
corpse of an animal. Okay, אבל טומאה דרבנן לא. aval tumah d'rabanan
lo.
But do we say for a rabbinic טומאה tumah it's lighter so
we're not going to make it come back? And what about עבודה
זרה? avodah zarah? Yeah, which is the טומאה tumah is only rabbinic.
The עבודה זרה avodah zarah is דאורייתא, d'oraita, the טומאה tumah is
דרבנן. d'rabanan. או דלמא, O dilma, or do we say לא שנא,
lo shena, it doesn't matter, it also comes back for a rabbinic
טומאה. tumah. So the גמרא Gemara says ותיבעי ליה שאר טומאות דרבנן,
vetiba'ei lei shear tumot d'rabanan, so why did you start by an
עבודה זרה avodah zarah case? חדא מיגו חדא קמיבעיא ליה. Chada migu
chada kamba'ei lei. Yes, it's like one question built on another. טומאה
דרבנן מי הדרה ליה? Tumah d'rabanan mi hadra lei? First question is,
would a normal טומאה דרבנן tumah d'rabanan come back? ואם תמצא לומר
לא הדרה, Ve'im timtza lomar lo hadra, and even if you were
to say a normal טומאה דרבנן tumah d'rabanan wouldn't come back when
you reshape the vessel, so טומאה דעבודת כוכבים, tumah d'avodat kochavim, what
about a טומאה tumah of עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? משום חומרא דעבודת
כוכבים משוויה רבנן כטומאה דאורייתא או לא? Mishum chumra d'avodat kochavim mashveiya
rabanan ketumah d'oraita o lo?
Because of the weightiness of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, would we put
that in the דאורייתא d'oraita category even though technically it's דרבנן d'rabanan
to say it would come back? תיקו, Teiku, so we don't have
an answer. So now we don't know what happens if you break
it and whatever if the טומאה tumah comes back. And we also
don't know if the תשמיש tashmish of an עבודה זרה avodah zarah
of a Jew where the idol is forbidden right away, is the
תשמיש tashmish forbidden right away. Okay, now בעי מיניה רבי יוחנן מרבי
ינאי. ba'ei minei Rebbi Yochanan me'Rebbi Yannai. Now that we're talking about
טומאה tumah by עבודה זרה avodah zarah and when does it come
back, we're going to ask some related questions.
תקרובת עבודת כוכבים, Tikrovet avodat kochavim, you have an object that was
offered as a, you know, as an offering to the gods. תקרובת,
Tikrovet, which is as we know אסורה, asura, it's טמא tamei like
a מת, met, can't even be ביטול. bitul. Okay. Wait, did you
skip?
Did I skip?
רבי יוחנן מרבי ינאי. Rebbi Yochanan me'Rebbi Yannai.
Did I skip it? Okay, maybe I did skip it. Okay, בעי
מיניה רבי יוחנן מרבי ינאי. Ba'ei minei Rebbi Yochanan me'Rebbi Yannai. I
think I read that. תקרובת עבודת כוכבים של אוכלין מהו?
Tikrovet avodat kochavim shel
ochlin mahu? Okay, מי מהני להו ביטול לטהרינו מטומאה או לא? mi
mahani lehu bitul letahareinu mitumah o lo? So somebody goes ahead and
brings I don't know some fruit to Zeus, it's a תקרובת, tikrovet,
it's now טמא. tamei. Okay, now they're going to do ביטול. bitul.
Will the ביטול bitul make the טומאה tumah go away? And here's
the reason for the question. We know the ביטול bitul makes the
status of the idol go away and the idol becomes מותר בהנאה
mutar be'hana'ah and it makes it become also מותר mutar and there's
no טומאה. tumah. But the ביטול bitul doesn't work for תקרובת, tikrovet,
remember that הלכה? halacha? ביטול bitul doesn't work for תקרובת. tikrovet. But
would it work enough to make the טומאה tumah go away? That's
the question. Okay. של אוכלין מהו? shel ochlin mahu? מי מהני להו
ביטול לטהרינו מטומאה או לא? Mi mahani lehu bitul letahareinu mitumah o
lo? ותיבעי ליה כלים, Vetiba'ei lei kelim, why not ask about vessels?
Why did you emphasize food? Okay. כלים לא קא מיבעיא ליה. keilim
lo ka mi'bai'yei lei. No, no. כלים keilim I get. כיון דאית
להו טהרה במקוה, טומאה נמי בטלה. keivan de'is lehu taharah b'mikvah tumah
nami bitlah. A status the טומאה tumah status of a כלי kli
is more flexible because in other cases, like normal laws of טומאה,
tumah, you can dunk it in a מקוה. mikvah. So something that's
טמא tamei is not a permanent identity if it's a כלי. kli.
So there I'm willing to accept that even though it's תקרובת, tikroves,
once there's ביטול, bitul, the טומאה tumah goes off because טומאה tumah
is not as tightly tied in with its identity. But a food,
טומאה tumah never goes off. So by food, that is the question,
you know, and it's a תקרובת, tikroves, which also the איסור issur
status doesn't go off. Will that, so that's a reason to think
the טומאה tumah doesn't go off either. So כיון דאית להו טהרה
במקוה keivan de'is lehu taharah b'mikvah, טומאה נמי בטלה. tumah nami bitlah.
כי קא מיבעיא ליה אוכלין. ki ka mi'bai'yei lei ochlin. The question
is food. ואי תיבעי לך עבודה זרה גופה, v'i tibei lach avodah
zarah gufah, so ask about if somebody worshipped worshipped an apple. Why
are you asking about תקרובת? tikroves? So as I've been saying, it's
because it has both חומרות chumros combined here. No. עבודה זרה גופה
לא מיבעיא ליה. avodah zarah gufah lo mi'bai'yei lei. That's not a
problem. כיון דאיסורא בטל, keivan d'issura batel, since actually its איסור issur
status goes away, you can even get הנאה hana'ah from it, you
know, you can use it to
pave your streets or whatever. טומאה נמי
בטלה. tumah nami bitlah. The איסור issur is the biblical status. The
טומאה tumah is the rabbinic status. So the טומאה tumah which is
secondary, if the איסור issur status goes away, the טומאה tumah status
definitely goes away. כי קא מיבעיא ליה תקרובת עבודה זרה של אוכלין.
ki ka mi'bai'yei lei tikroves avodah zarah shel ochlin. I want to
know the combination of these two. מה? mah? What do we say?
On the one hand, it's food. So already the טומאה tumah status
is more closely connected to it. It's not as it's not as,
like, you know, transitory. Or it's not transitory at all. Number two,
the איסור issur status doesn't go away. כיון דאיסורא לא בטל, keivan
d'issura lo batel, since the איסור issur status doesn't go away, כדרב
גידל, k'rav gidal, like רב גידל rav gidal like we taught the
other day, טומאה נמי לא בטלה, tumah nami lo bitlah, the טומאה
tumah doesn't go away. או דלמא, o dilma, or do we say,
איסור דאורייתא לא בטל, issur d'oraisa lo batel, no, at the end
of the day, the איסור issur is a תורה torah status and
that doesn't go away. טומאה דרבנן, tumah d'rabanan, and טומאה tumah is
only rabbinic, so once ביטול bitul was done, at least the טומאה
tumah status would go away. So בטלה, bitlah, that does go
away. תיקו. teiku. Once again, we don't know. But that's a nice
question, right? We obviously the טומאה tumah status follows the איסור, issur,
if the איסור issur goes away, the טומאה tumah goes away. But
in תקרובת, tikroves, where there's ביטול bitul and it's still אסור, assur,
what about the טומאה tumah status, especially if it's food, and we
don't have an answer.
You can give meaning to like in-between though, the expression
your body's your temple.
Your body's your temple, right. Okay. בעי מיניה רב יוסף בן שמואל
מרבי. bai minei rav yosef ben shmuel me'rebi. So here's another question.
כלים, keilim, this is gonna be fun. כלים ששימשו בהן בבית חוניו
מהו שישתמשו בהן בבית המקדש? keilim she'shimshu bahen b'veis chonyo mahu she'ishtamshu
bahen b'veis hamikdash? Okay. Now בית חוניו, beis chonyo, during the period
of the Hasmonean period, there was this חוניו chonyo was one of
the sons of שמעון הצדיק. shimon hatzadik. He ran away because he
was afraid that he was going to get
whatever you know executed, not executed, assassinated by his brother. And he
went to Egypt and he established a temple there. Okay. And the
whole question was what was going on exactly in that temple? Were
they worshipping God and then it was an איסור issur of a
במה, bamah, worshipping God out you know bringing sacrifices outside of the
בית המקדש, beis hamikdash, or was it actually עבודה זרה? avodah zarah?
Okay. So where, so we want to know if you had some
nice beautiful you know knives and and bowls and whatever gold things
and now you want to use them in the בית המקדש. beis
hamikdash. Are they off limits or not? Now you'll all remember that
something that was actually used for עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, even when
the איסור issur status goes away, or even if it never got
the איסור issur status like you worshipped a mountain or whatever or
a tree and so on, the objects are forbidden to use in
the בית המקדש. beis hamikdash. That was an earlier discussion. Okay.
But here, so if it was really for עבודה זרה avodah zarah
it wouldn't be an issue even if there was ביטול. bitul. But
the question is if it weren't used for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
Okay. Okay. מהו? mahu? כלים ששימשו בבית חוניו מהו שישתמשו בהן בבית
המקדש? keilim she'shimshu b'veis chonyo mahu she'ishtamshu bahen b'veis hamikdash?
So the גמרא gemara says וכי קא מיבעיא ליה אליבא דמאן דאמר
וכי קא מיבעיא ליה אליבא דמאן דאמר בית חוניו לאו בית עבודה
זרה היא. v'chi ka mi'bai'yei lei aliba d'man d'amar v'chi ka mi'bai'yei
lei aliba d'man d'amar beis chonyo lav beis avodah zarah hi. And
this is assuming it's not a בית עבודה זרה. beis avodah zarah.
If it was a בית עבודה זרה beis avodah zarah the answer
would be obvious. דתנן, d'tanan, now what's דתנן d'tanan because the משנה
mishnah says: כהנים ששימשו בבית חוניו לא ישמשו במקדש
שבירושלים. kohanim she'shimshu b'veis chonyo lo yishamshu b'mikdash she'b'yerushalayim. כהנים kohanim that
served in בבית חוניו beis chonyo cannot come back now and and
you know be do their עבודה avoda in the בית המקדש beis
hamikdash in ירושלים. yerushalayim. ואינו צריך לומר לדבר אחר. v'eino tzarich lomar
l'davar acher. It goes without saying if these כהנים kohanim were actually
involved in עבודה זרה avodah zarah they can't serve anymore in the
בית המקדש, beis hamikdash, but even that's דבר אחר davar acher means.
But even if they weren't involved in עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, just
בית חוניו, beis chonyo, they also can't serve. So that makes it
pretty clear that it's not treating בית חוניו beis chonyo as עבודה
זרה. avodah zarah. Okay. So כהנים, kohanim, so
now we got it. בית חוניו beis chonyo isn't עבודה זרה avodah
zarah but nevertheless the כהנים kohanim can't serve here if they served
there. So the question is what about the כלים? keilim? Okay.
So כהנים הוא דקנסינהו רבנן. kohanim hu d'kansinhu rabanan. Do we say
the fine was applied to כהנים kohanim משום דבני דעה נינהו mishum
d'vnei de'ah ninhu
because they have intellect? They could have chosen not to go there.
They're fined. You made that choice, now you are permanently stigmatized because
it was a choice you made. Okay. אבל כלים לא? aval keilim
lo? But the poor vessels, they didn't get to choose where they
were going to be used, so the stigma... also, it's not just
like, you know, who are we fining, who are we punishing by
making the vessels unusable, but the כהנים Kohanim clearly you're being punished
for your bad choice. So one way it could seem like is
it serving the goal of punishment or not, in one case yes
and the other no. The other also point could be the degree
to which we associate a stigma with it. You as a person
of free will made a choice, so your bad decisions and the
things you did more stigmatize you because those were choices that you
made. Whereas if somebody came and used a vessel to do something
disgusting with it, why should that affect the status of the vessel?
We do say that it does. We do sometimes, right? Like מצוה
הבאה בעבירה mitzvah ha'ba'ah b'aveirah and whatever, I mean there are cases
where we do, but not to the same degree, that's the point.
Of course you could say the opposite. A person who makes choices
and who is, you know, dynamic and not static also can do
תשובה teshuvah and a person should not constantly be, you know, be,
you know, be stigmatized and be, you know, framed and defined by
his earlier actions, especially if he can change, you know, where a
vessel is more static and maybe it does keep the status. Anyway,
interesting different ways of thinking about it, but that's the point. Maybe
we only fine the priests, we don't do this to the vessels.
אידי
ואידי לא שנא, idi v'idi lo shana, it doesn't matter. אמר ליה
אסורין הן, amar lei assurin hen, you know what, it's forbidden. ומקרא
היה בידינו ושכחנוה. umikra haya b'yadeinu v'shachachnuha. We actually had a פסוק.
pasuk. Now of course a פסוק pasuk isn't going to talk about
בית חוניו, Beit Chonyo, but we had a פסוק pasuk that we
could have used to make an analogy that would have been relevant
to teach us that even though technically it should be okay and
it's even though it's only about inanimate objects, we should still say
it's off limits, but I forgot what the פסוק pasuk was. I
had a good פסוק pasuk to prove this, I forgot it. איתיבי,
eitivei, okay so that was so who was asking this from whom?
רבי יוסי בן שאול Rabbi Yossi ben Shaul asked רבי Rebbi this.
So then רבי Rebbi said it's אסור. assur. So רבי יוסי בן
שאול Rabbi Yossi ben Shaul said, wait, I'll bring a פסוק pasuk
to show you that it should be מותר. muttar. What's the פסוק?
pasuk? כל הכלים אשר הזניח המלך אחז במלכותו במעלו. kol hakeilim asher
hizniach hamelech achaz b'malchuto b'ma'alo. So this is in the time of
I think it was חזקיהו, Chizkiyahu, right? What'd רש"י Rashi say?
חזקיהו. Chizkiyahu. So it says all of the vessels that King Achaz
used when he, like he took these temple vessels and he used
them for עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, okay, and he profaned them, הכנו
והקדשנו, hichanu v'hikdashnu,
they basically, we have like prepared them and sanctified them for use
in the Temple. So you have vessels that were used for עבודה
זרה avodah zarah that are somehow being, temple vessels that are now
being sanctified and put back into use. So now the assumption here
is, since they were temples of the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, he
had no way to make them forbidden because they weren't his, they
belong to the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, they were קדש. kodesh. So
technically these vessels were never forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, but they went
through some process, but after a process, after which process they were
reused. So therefore רבי יוסי בן שאול Rabbi Yossi ben Shaul is
saying, here's an evidence, okay, that actually it can be reused. All
right, something that was problematic although not technically forbidden, like בית חוניו,
Beit Chonyo, and then you do some ritual and then you can
reuse
it. מאי לאו הכנו דאטבלינהו. mai lav hichanu d'atblinhu. הכנו, hichanu, we
prepared them, means we put them in a מקוה. mikvah. הקדשנו, hikdashnu,
and we sanctified
them, דאקדשיננהו. d'akdashinunhu. Anyway, that we re-sanctified them. But even so, we
did some ritual but now they're able to be reused.
Yeah, but don't we usually say הזניח hizniach means that they weren't
used, like, no, הזניח, hizniach, yeah but it means like he disgraced
them. What?
That would be the modern Hebrew.
Yeah, the modern Hebrew, but here it also means like he disgraced
them or
whatever.
Anyway, אמר ליה, amar
lei, yeah
he used them for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Okay, so look, here's
something was used for עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, not technically forbidden because
it wasn't, didn't belong to him, it belonged to the בית המקדש,
Beit Hamikdash, but it can be and be reused. So בית חוניו
Beit Chonyo isn't technically forbidden, but we should be able to reuse
the vessels. אמר ליה, amar lei, so רבי Rebbi said back to
him, ברוך אתה לשמים שהחזרת לי אבידתי. baruch atah l'shamayim shehichzarta li
aveidati. Oh, you returned my lost object! You quoted that פסוק, pasuk,
that was the פסוק pasuk I was thinking about! But of course
I read it the exact opposite as you. Okay, הכנו, hichanu, we
prepared them, שגנזום. shegenazum. It doesn't mean that we actually reused these
vessels. We did with them what needed to be done, we put
them in גניזה, gnizah, these old temple vessels. והקדשנו, v'hikdashnu, שהקדשנו אחרים
תחתיהם, shehikdashnu acherim tachteiahem, we sanctified new vessels. So I read this
the exact opposite as you, you can't reuse them. Okay, לימא מסייעא
ליה, leima mesayeia lei, let's try to bring a proof to רבי.
Rebbi. מזרחית צפונית, mizrachit tzonit, okay these are the different sort of,
you know, chambers in the עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim in the בית
המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. So the north-eastern chamber, בה גנזו בית חשמונאי אבני
מזבח ששקצו אנשי יון. bah ganazu beit chashmonai avnei mizbeiach sheshiktzu anshei
yavan. That's where the stones of the altar that had been defiled
when the, you know, the Greeks, Seleucids, took over the בית המקדש,
Beit Hamikdash, right before the, right before the miracle of חנוכה, Chanukah,
okay, so they defiled those stones and therefore they put them into
גניזה gnizah after they re-sanctified the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. Okay, so,
ואמר רב ששת v'amar Rav Sheshet ששקצום לעבודה זרה. sheshiktzum l'avodah zarah.
They had used those stones for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So why
is that parallel? Because... Again, the Greeks have no ability to make
the stones forbidden. It's not theirs. They can't, even if they worshipped
it as עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, whatever, they can't make it forbidden.
It's not theirs. But nevertheless, since it was used for עבודה זרה,
Avodah Zarah, we're not going to use it in the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, we're going to bury it. So it's another case of
something that's not technically forbidden, but still we're going to choose to
make it- to keep it off-limits. And the same by parallel, the
same- in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, they didn't use the מנורה
menorah for their whatever? Well, they made a new מנורה, menorah, that's
the whole story about whatever. Anyway, so therefore,
so in a similar, now of course you could still say עבודה
זרה's Avodah Zarah worse than other things, but similarly we see כלים
keilim that are used for an improper purpose even if they don't
get a status, a particular הלכתי halachic status, we're going to bury
them and keep them off-limits. Okay, that maybe is a support for
רבי. Rebbi. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב פפא Amar Rav
Pappa no. התם קרא אשכח ודרש. Hatam kra ashkhach v'darash. There, actually
it actually might have been really הלכתית halachically forbidden based on a
verse. What was the verse? They found a verse, דכתיב ובאו בה
פריצים וחיללוה. dikhtiv u-bau-vo pritzim v'chilliluha The- the- פריצים pritzim is not
profaners, those that burst through, the violators came and desecrated it. Okay,
which- the point was when the non-Jews took
over the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it actually made the objects become
unsanctified.
Okay, that's what you learn from that verse. If you look at
רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, where's רש"י? Rashi? Two lines before the
lines get wide, קרא אשכח ודרש kra ashkhach v'darash מדאורייתא אסירי אפילו
להדיוט mi-doraisa asirei afilu l'hedyot דכתיב dikhtiv ובאו בה פריצים וחיללוה u-bau-vo
pritzim v'chilliluha. כיון שנכנסו keivan shenikhnesu עובדי כוכבים להיכל ovdei kochavim l'heikhal
יצאו כליו לחולין. yatzu keilav l'chullin. It went- they became- they become
defiled or whatever unsanctified, they became desecrated. So this, by the way,
is a very important- wait, so then you could actually use them?
Or does it mean they become חולין chullin you can use them?
Well, A, you could use them and B, they could make them
into עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. Once they lost their sanctity, they really
did become עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So then they really couldn't be
used afterwards.
So then I can use the מזבח mizbe'ach for like my private
table now or whatever?
If they had- if it hadn't been worshipped as עבודה זרה, Avodah
Zarah, yes. Okay, the גמרא's Gemara going to get to that. By
the way, this becomes a very important question הלכתית, halachically, what exactly
is the scope of this? How much does this literally mean it,
as Michael's asking? And the question happened about when synagogues were, you
know, were destroyed by non-Jews, the Nazi period, other periods or whatever,
what does that do to the sanctity of the objects? Does this
concept of ובאו בה פריצים וחיללוה u-bau-vo pritzim v'chilliluha apply to synagogues
and other types of things?
And what did it mean 'became in'?
They come in, that's it? No, it means they walked in. They
were פריצים. pritzim. They violated it, they took it over, they kicked
the Jews out. Okay, that's what it means. But they haven't had
to do
any עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah yet, so they just came in and
said you're out?
Yeah, exactly. By seizing it, that was the חילולה, chillula, right, not
the act of עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. The seizing of it of
it was the act of the- of the חילולה. chillula. It was
the- they were פריצים, pritzim, that was the problem. They weren't invited
guests, they were gatecrashers. Okay, that's actually pretty figurative of פריצים pritzim
לפרוץ, lifrotz, they were gatecrashers. Okay, anyway, אמר היכי נעביד. amar heikhi
na'avid. Now they made this all non-sanctified and they worshipped it and
now it's real עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So what should we do
with these stones? נתברינהו, nitbrinhu,
let's break them. רש"י Rashi says it means let's get a non-Jew
to do ביטול bitul and then break it and then it'll become
מותר muttar again, okay. אבנים שלמות אמר רחמנא. avanim shelemos amar Rachmana.
No, you have to use whole stones. נתברינהו, nitbrinhu,
okay, after a non-Jew breaks it and does ביטול, bitul, let's shave
it down and so that it would be smooth. לא תניף עליהם
ברזל אמר רחמנא. Lo tanif aleihem barzel amar Rachmana. You can't- you
can't use iron. ואמאי, v'amai, says the גמרא, Gemara, so why is
that a problem? לתברינהו ולשקלינהו לנפשיהו, litbrinhu v'lishklinu l'nafshaihu,
like Michael says. Go ahead and okay get a non-Jew to do
ביטול bitul on them. The ובאו בה פריצים וחיללוה u-bau-vo pritzim v'chilliluha
made it non-הקדש. hekdesh. Now it's- they worshipped it, it's עבודה זרה.
Avodah Zarah. Get a non-Jew to do ביטול bitul and now go
ahead and use it to pave your streets, okay, if it's really
not הקדש hekdesh anymore. מי לא אמר רבי יאשיה mi lo amar
Rabbi Yoshia ביקשו לגנוז כלי כסף וזהב שבעולם משום כספו וזהבו של
ירושלים, bikshu lignoz klei kesef v'zahav sheba'olam mishum kaspo v'zahavo shel Yerushalayim,
that they wanted to make all gold and silver in the world
forbidden because it- because of the concern of the gold and silver
in ירושלים Yerushalayim that was הקדש hekdesh and that was maybe like
seized by the Romans and then put into currency and so on.
So the גמרא Gemara says ואוינן בה, v'avinan bo, yeah, wait a
minute, ירושלים הוי רובא דעלמא? Yerushalayim had ruba d'alma? I don't get
it. There was so much gold in ירושלים Yerushalayim that all gold
and silver now is the majority gold and silver found in the
world? גזונטהייט. Gezuntheit.
אלא אמר אביי Ella amar Abaye ביקשו לגנוז דינרא
הדרינא וטוריינא שיפא מפני טיבעה של ירושלים. bikshu lignoz dinra hadriyana turyana
shayfa mipnei tiva shel Yerushalayim. No, no. It's specific types of coinages.
The coins of רש"י Rashi says it's Hadrian and probably these other
types of Roman coins. And רש"י Rashi says the word שיפא shayfa
means and that the face of it had been what like rubbed
out. So because the face was rubbed out, maybe you couldn't tell,
maybe it originally had been a ירושלים Yerushalayim coin. It's not clear
if the concern is this was originally a ירושלים Yerushalayim coin that
had been- the image had been rubbed out or is the point
still that they took all that gold and silver, they melted it
down and then they, you know, recirculated it. Okay, but whatever it
is, in a certain type of a circumstance, they were concerned about
using that gold and silver because it might have come from the
sanctified gold and silver in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. מפני טיבעה של ירושלים. mipnei
tiva shel Yerushalayim. So now how did they, what allowed them to
do it? עד שמצאו לו מקרא מן התורה שהוא מותר ובאו בו
פריצים וחיללוה. ad shematzu lo mikra min hatorah shemutar uvau vo pritzim
v'chiluloh. Now when they invaded and took over the בית המקדש Beit
Hamikdash and seized the gold and silver, presumably now we're talking about
in the time of the
Romans' destruction of the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, no longer the Greeks.
Okay, that made the gold and silver, that took it out of
its sanctity. So you see, it's just like Michael said. Once it's
removed from its sanctity, you can actually use it for personal use.
So why didn't they decide to use the stones for personal use?
So the גמרא Gemara says, התם לא אשתמשו בהו לגבוה. hatam lo
ishtamshu bahu l'gavoah. No, the gold and silver might have been sanctified,
but it wasn't actually used directly in the temple. It was there
to buy temple objects. הכא. hacha.
So they're not talking about the כלי שרת klei sharet then?
No, right. They're talking, it says טיבעה של ירושלים, tiva shel Yerushalayim,
so it's talking about like the coins. It's a good question. I
guess the כלי שרת klei sharet weren't enough to be concerned about.
הכא כיון דאשתמיש בו לגבוה, hacha keivan d'ishtamish bo l'gavoah,
since the stones were used, לאו אורחא לאשתמושי בהדיוט. lav orcha l'ishtamushi
b'hedyot. Technically it's no longer הקדש hekdesh anymore, but it's not דרך
ארץ, derech eretz, so this is your classic גניזה. gnizah. Okay, actually
this is now the double גניזה, gnizah, right? It's the גניזה gnizah
because it's עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. But it's actually interesting, why would
they be allowed to do גניזה? gnizah? עבודה זרה avodah zarah they
should have to destroy it. Maybe they did do the ביטול. bitul.
But after they did the ביטול, bitul, right, then they still had
to be גונז goneiz it because it had been something that had
been הקדש. hekdesh. Okay, so this is a very important גמרא Gemara
about this.
But it wasn't עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
It was. The non-Jews, not the gold, the stones.
Oh, even the stones, I think it's גניזה gnizah because it was
מחולל mechulal but it can't.
Oh, you think in the end the גמרא Gemara isn't even assuming
that it was worshipped? You think that in the end once it
gets to this idea that you had to do גניזה gnizah it
wasn't even based on the fact that it was worshipped?
איפכא מבי כחניא, ifcha mibei chanya, it's not עבודה זרה avodah zarah
but you have to.
Maybe. I was still assuming that the גמרא Gemara was working with
the phrase ששיקצו. sheshiktzu. I mean, but שיקצו shiktzu could mean שיקצו
shiktzu just that they defiled it. It's a good point. I hear
your question, right? The question is like maybe in the end since
גניזה gnizah is required just the fact that they were הקדש hekdesh
we're not even assuming it was עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. It's just
because of the הקדש hekdesh it was גניזה. gnizah. That could be.
Yeah, it relates to the previous עמוד amud that גניזה gnizah is
used where something shouldn't be used because it doesn't have a status,
like the אשרה Asherah of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. ישראל Yisrael didn't
worship it, so it doesn't have a status of עבודה זרה avodah
zarah but you still can't have it as an אשרה. Asherah. Right,
right, right.
So
in the end the גמרא Gemara doesn't conclude about בית חוניו, Beit
Chonyo, you could argue either way. And it's interesting this case, but
this case about the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash is very important, this
principle of ובאו פריצים וחיללוה, uvau pritzim v'chiluloh, does it have broader
ramifications? Is it just about the בית המקדש? Beit Hamikdash? But the
גמרא Gemara treats it as very serious, that it does take the
things that are הקדש hekdesh and the act of being violated de-sanctifies
them. Okay, and it's a very interesting, you know, powerful halakhic idea.
Okay, but whether then something that didn't get a status actually but
somehow was used in an inappropriate way can then be repurposed in
the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, that we really have an answer. All
right, let's start the next משנה. mishnah. עובד כוכבים מבטל עבודת כוכבים
שלו ושל חברו. oved kochavim mevatel avodat kochavim shelo veshel chaveiro. Very
appropriately since we've been talking about ביטול bitul so far and it's
also talking about like these, like the mirror images of Jew and
non-Jew. So a non-Jew can nullify his idol and even an idol
he doesn't own, which is pretty amazing if you think about it.
Right, here's Michael's idol, you know, here's whatever, okay, Michael's idol, he's
a non-Jew and I can come ahead and I can change its
status as far
as Jews are concerned. Like presumably Michael still thinks it's a god
and he's still going to worship it or whatever. And I guess
if he continued to worship it after I ביטלתי bitalti it, that
would make it... that would make it אסור assur again. But if
a Jew swoops in in that interim, it's a pretty amazing idea
that a non-Jew can מבטל mevatel something he has no rights to
and he has no say about. Can I do it if I'm...
if I'm a Saturn worshiper and he's a Zeus worshiper and I
have never, and I think those Zeus worshipers are crazy, right, and
I completely reject his whole idea. Can I also be מבטל mevatel
it? Do I have to be related to the same sort of
faith system? It doesn't seem. It seems like everybody's just being thrown
into one huge category. All non-Jews are the same. It's all the
same big עבודה זרה avodah zarah and anybody can be מבטל mevatel
anybody else's עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. An עבודה זרה גוי. avodah zarah
goy. Exactly. Like a שבת גוי. Shabbat goy. Yeah. Okay, anyway, okay.
וישראל אין מבטל עבודת כוכבים של עובד כוכבים. v'yisrael ein mevatel avodat
kochavim shel oved kochavim. And a Jew can't be מבטל mevatel the
עבודה זרה avodah zarah of a non-Jew. Yeah, if he could, that
would get rid of all the הלכות halachot of destroying and הנאה.
hana'ah. המבטל עבודת כוכבים מבטל משמשיה. ham'vatel avodat kochavim m'vatel m'sham'sheha. As
soon as you're מבטל mevatel the עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, this was,
I didn't spell this out before because it wasn't clear in the
גמרא Gemara before. If a non-Jew is מבטל mevatel the Zeus statue,
all of the fire pans and all the things that are used
automatically become בטל batel because they're all connected to that to that
to that item. Okay, but ביטל משמשיה משמשיה מותרין והיא אסורה. bitel
m'sham'sheha m'sham'sheha mutarin v'hi asurah. You can be מבטל mevatel just the
fire pan and keep on worshipping Zeus, and the fire pan will
be permissible but the Zeus will be forbidden. Okay, so there you
can have ביטול bitul just on the משמשין, meshameshin, but if you
have ביטול bitul on the עבודה זרה avodah zarah it automatically is
מבטל mevatel the משמש. meshamesh. Makes a lot of sense. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. מתני ליה רבי לרבי שמעון בריה.
matni leh Rabbi l'Rabbi Shimon breih. So רבי Rabbi taught רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon his son, עובד כוכבים מבטל עבודת כוכבים שלו ושל חברו.
oved kochavim mevatel avodat kochavim shelo veshel chaveiro. What our משנה mishnah
says, a non-Jew can be מבטל mevatel his and his friend's. אמר
ליה רבי. amar leh Rabbi. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said to
his father, he called him רבי, Rabbi, רבי שנית לנו בילדותך, Rabbi
shonita lanu b'yaldutcha, when you were younger you taught us עובד כוכבים
מבטל עבודת כוכבים שלו ושל ישראל, oved kochavim mevatel avodat kochavim shelo
veshel Yisrael, that a non-Jew can... even be מבטל mevatel the idol
of a Jew. So what's the story? Have you reversed yourself? Yeah,
this is the evidence of the משנה'ס Mishna's writing. Yeah, exactly. And
we have this other places that רבי Rebbi said something earlier when
he was younger, later when he was older. So דישראל, D'Yisrael, so
now the גמרא Gemara says one minute, so the דישראל D'Yisrael before
רבי Rebbi gets a chance to answer or whatever, the גמרא Gemara
jumps in. דישראל מי קמבטל? D'Yisrael mi ka mevatel? One minute. Ha!
No, no, nobody ever would have said that you could do ביטול
bittul on an עבודה זרה avodah zarah of a Jew. ואפס אמתא
סתר כתיב. V'afas amsa sater ketiv. It says place it in hiding
which we learn how, I don't know how we learn that more
than אבד תאבדון, Abeid te'abdun, you know, the idea of destroying and
burning, but somehow from that we learn it's a permanent status. Nobody
can ever be מבטל mevatel the עבודה זרה avodah zarah of a
Jew. סו אמר רב הילל בריה דרבי ולס, So amar Rav Hillel
brei de'Rebbi Vallas, oh no, here was the scenario: that the Jew
and the non-Jew were joint owners and joint worshippers of this idol.
Okay, בילדותו מאי קסבר ובזקנותו מאי קסבר? B'yalduto mai kasavar u'veziknuto mai
kasavar? What were the two stages of רבי'ס Rebbi's opinions?
בילדותו סבר ישראל אדעתא דעכו"ם פלח.
B'yalduto savar
Yisrael adaata d'akum palach. You know Jews deep down are really, at
the end of the day they have a פינטל ייד. pintle Yid.
They really believe in God. So if they're worshipping non-Jews, it's because
the non-Jews are influencing them. So when he's worshipping this idol together,
and maybe specifically in a case of שותפות, shutfus, when he's worshipping
this idol that he owns jointly with the non-Jew, he's only doing
it connected like sort of as an add-on to the non-Jew's worship.
So therefore כיון דעכו"ם מבטל דנפשיה ישראל נמי מבטלה. Kivan d'akum mevatel
d'nafshei Yisrael nami mevatla. So once the non-Jew is מבטל mevatel the
עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, that's מבטל mevatel the Jew's status as well
because the Jew's status was never, in this scenario, had an independent
status of an עבודה זרה avodah zarah of a Jew. It was
an עבודה זרה avodah zarah that a Jew was worshipping with a
non-Jew and it was always defined through the non-Jew. So therefore ביטול
bittul can take place. ובזקנותו סבר, U'veziknuto savar, and when he got
old he held, ישראל אדעתא דנפשיה פלח. Yisrael adaata d'nafshei palach. Nah,
Jews know how to do עבודה זרה avodah zarah on their own.
And therefore it has an independent status of an idol of a
Jew. Okay, and I guess what we will do is כי קא
מבטל עבודת כוכבים דנפשיה ישראל לא בטיל. Ki ka mevatel avodat kochavim
d'nafshei Yisrael lo batel. He's only מבטל mevatel his own, he's not
מבטל mevatel that of a Jew. The Jew has a separate status
and therefore the עבודה זרה avodah zarah of a Jew cannot be
בטל. batel. Okay, so we will continue with this tomorrow.